Guide to the Stanford University, Department of Economics, Honors Theses
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University, Department of Economics, honors theses
1971-2008
SC4-3863
Stanford University. Department of Economics.
8 Linear feet (160 volumes in 17 boxes)
Honors theses written by undergraduate students in the Stanford University Department of Economics.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
This collection was transferred to the Stanford University Archives by the Department of Economics in several accessions. Additional theses were transferred by the Hume Writing Center in 2011.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least 48 hours in advance of intended use. No photocopies may be made.
Scope and Contents note
This collection consists of honors theses written by undergraduate students in the Stanford University Department of Economics.
Access Terms
Economics--Study and teaching (Higher).; Student papers.
Collection Contents
- Theses, pre-1989
  - Angelillo, Neil, Tax Reform and Real Estate: The Effect on REITs., June 4, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Bakkensen, Ralph, A comparative analysis of the impact on social welfare of Oregon's "Bottle Bill" and Washington's "Model Litter Control Act"., June 6, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Basham, Mindy, Interstate Banking: A Time for Change., June 1, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Bertelson, Robert C., An Analysis of the Impact of Money Market Funds on Financial Intermediation in the United States., June 4, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Christopher, Robert Artie, Garlic in Gilroy: an analysis of the American fresh garlic industry. Anna Laura Myers Prize., May 1976 (Box 1)
  - Cooperman, Wayne, Commodity Bonds as a New and Betther Method of Lending to the Third World., 1988 (Box 1)
  - Corl, James S., The Tax Reform Act of 1986: Capital and the Prospects for Fairness, Simplicity, and Growth., 1988 (Box 1)
  - Covinton, Matthes S., Political Business Cycles in the United States., 1988 (Box 1)
  - Ernst, Joanne Alice, An analysis of increasing concentration in the United States brewing industry. [missing], June 1982
  - Fairlie, Robert, The Demand for Direct Service Airline Travel., June 4, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Fenyo, Kenneth, Fairness, Simplicity and Growth: The Politics and Economics of Tax Reform., 1988 (Box 2)
  - Flamm, Ken, Cows and conflict: the political economy of beef consumption in Chile., June 1973 (Box 2)
  - Gash, John, A Test of Semi-Strong Form Efficiency in the Stock Market., 1988 (Box 2)
  - Harrison, Craig R., The determining of program structure and benefit liberality of unemployment insurance in the United States. Anna Laura Myers Prize., May 1976 (Box 2)
  - Hellman, Robert B. Jr., Investment Durability Bias, An Analysis of the Economic Recovery Act of 1981., June 4, 1982 (Box 2)
  - Horn, Michael, An analysis of gold markets., 1979 (Box 2)
  - Hu, Wei-Yin, Wage, Employment and Gender Effects of Comparable Worth in San Jose., 1988 (Box 2)
  - Ingram, William D., Regional economic integration in Western Africa Ghana, and the Ivory Coast: a case study. Anna Laura Myers Prize., 1979 (Box 3)
  - Johnson, Diane C., Educational Reform: Bringing Efficiencey to Schools., June 1, 1984 (Box 3)
  - Kriger, Adam M., Education Production Functions: the Educational Economies of Integration., 1988 (Box 3)
  - Luczo, Stephen James, An economic explanation of the Black fertility decrease in the U. S. South 1895-1940. (Box 3)
  - Mason, Herbert O., Farm labor unionism in the Kern county table grape industry: an economic perspective., May 1971 (Box 3)
  - Matheson, Scott, Interfuel Competition and Energy Concentration. Anna Laura Myers Prize., October 1974 (Box 3)
  - Miller, Timothey M., The Japanese Success in the American Auto Market., 1988 (Box 3)
  - Miracky, William, Stabilization Policy in the Open Economy Under Imperfect Capital Mobility., June 1987 (Box 3)
  - Moghadam, Kimya, The Latin American Debt Crisis., June 1984 (Box 3)
  - Muth, Daniel F., An Analysis of the Interaction of Stock Market Prices with Real Macro-economic Behavior., 1988 (Box 4)
  - Page, John M., Jr., The automobile assembly industry and regional economic growth in northern Chile., May 1970 (Box 4)
  - Raphael, Scott D., An economic analysis of the air traffic congestion problem at Los Angeles International Airport: seeking a short-rn solution. Anna Laura Myers Prize., 1979 (Box 4)
  - Rasinki, Susan, Foreign Debt: Factors Leading up to Mexico's 1982 Financial Crisis., 1984 (Box 4)
  - Ratner, Morrie, Optimial Liability in the Asbestos context., 1988 (Box 4)
  - Sidak, Joseph Gregory, Antitrust treble damages and economic efficiency. Anna Laura Myers Prize., 1977 (Box 4)
  - Simon, Perry, Market population and radio programming diversity: a theoretical, empirical, and policy analysis. Anna Laura Myers Prize., 1977 (Box 4)
  - Slipe, Rebecca, Closing the Wage Gap. The Experience of the 1980s., 1988 (Box 4)
  - Stupfel, Mark J., The nature of exposure and optimal hedging strategies for a trading firm. [missing], May 1981
  - Vayle, Eric J., Specific Factors in Britain: Explaining the Relation of Sectoral Upheaval to the Economic Decline of Late-Victorian Britain., 1988 (Box 4)
  - Wernecke, William A., The mixed corporation model in Brazil: a case analysis of three state steel firms. 1964-1976. Anna Laura Myers Prize., 1977 (Box 4)
  - Wymore, Bruce Edward, The Role of Expected Inflation and Consumer Uncertainty in Determining Consumption Behavior. Anna Laura Myers Prize., June 1975 (Box 4)
- Theses, Accession ARCH-1989-116
  - Al-Jubeir, Mahar, The Hidden Cost of Taxing Oil Imports: Analyzing the Oil Import Tax., May 1989 (Box 1)
  - Chang, Steven, Security Market Returns: An Application of the Switching Regression Model with Endogenous Multiswitching., May 1989 (Box 1)
  - Gerstman, Gary D., Western Joint Ventures in the USSR: An Evaluation of Problems and Prospects., May 1989 (Box 1)
  - Hedien, Mark J., Lending to Latin American Governments 1820-1914: Penalties for Default., May 1989 (Box 1)
  - Honerkamp, John, Listen to the Technology: A Case Against Federal Funding of Commercial R&D., 1989-90 (Box 1)
  - Jones, Christopher L., Nonlinear Neural Network Models for Economic Time Series Analysis., May 1989 (Box 1)
  - Lau, Lucius B., An Analysis of Trad Policy and the US Steel Industry., June 1989 (Box 2)
  - Levey, Brian H., Should We Throw "Sand in the Gears"?: An Analysis of Financial Regulatioin in Wake of Black Monday., June 1989 (Box 2)
  - Mayer, Lloyd, Poverty in the United States: A Public Policy Approach., May 1989 (Box 2)
  - Moss, Jonathan, Is a Housing Allowance a Satisfactory Response to Our Nation's Housing Crisis., 1989 (Box 2)
  - Norris, Craig D., Winner Takes All: College Football Television in the Aftermath of 'NCAA v. Board of Regents of the University of Oklahoma., May 1989 (Box 2)
  - Schmidt, Stephen, The Sensitivity of the United States to Income Inequality, 1964-1982., May 1989 (Box 2)
  - Taychakhoonavudh, Neeracha, Thailand's Development As A Newly Industrialized Country., May 1989 (Box 2)
- Theses, Accession ARCH-1990-132
  - Barnett, Steven, Regional Decentralization of the Soviet Economy., 1990 (Box 1)
  - Beasley, Allen, Health Care Market Failures in the US: Problems of Cost-containment and Access., 1990 (Box 1)
  - Bhattacharya, Jayanta, Medical Malpractice Risk and Physician Specialty Choice: A Study., 1990 (Box 1)
  - Bridwell, Paul, A Financial Analysis of Capital Intensity in the Integrated circuit Industry., 1990 (Box 1)
  - Epstein, Rebecca L., An Evaluation of the Depository Institutions Deregulation and Monetary Control Act: The Effects on the Value of Thrift Institutions., 1990 (Box 1)
  - Feferman, Flavio, A Regional Profile of Technology in Brazilian Agriculture with Some Implictions for Rural Employment., 1990 (Box 1)
  - Gustafson, Stephen Philip, An Analysis of the Integrated Circuit Industry in the United States and Japan: The Role for US Government Policy., 1990 (Box 2)
  - Jones, David L., Industry Effects of the Switch from Fixed to Floating Exchange Rate Regimes on the Volatility of Equity Risk Premiums., 1990 (Box 2)
  - Lee, Julie Juhyun, Empirical Performance of the Efficient Contract Model of Union-Management Bargaining., 1990 (Box 2)
  - Lim, Jae Y., Regression Analysis on Medicare Expenditures and the Effect of the Prospective Payment System., 1990 (Box 2)
  - Sarathy, Sanjay, An Economic Analysis of India's Foreign Exchange Regulatory Act of 1973., 1990 (Box 2)
  - Sarkis, Ziad, Pure Expectations., 1990 (Box 2)
  - Strumpf, Koleman, Towards an Effort System of Economic Justice., 1990 (Box 2)
  - Vazquez, Mitchelle, The Impact of Corporate Takeovers on Labor in the United States., 1990 (Box 2)
  - Waggoner, Ellen, The Performances of the American and British Television Industries: An Economic Analysis of their Differing Program Mixes., 1990 (Box 2)
- Theses, Accession ARCH-1991-092
  - Akers, Kim, Overpaid Boys or Underpaid Men: The Salary Determination Process in the NBA., 1991 (Box 1)
  - Berk, Karen, Bank Reform: Inaction due to Econmoic and Political Conflict., 1991 (Box 1)
  - Blosser, Shawn, Privation in East Germany: What Makes it So Special?., 1991 (Box 1)
  - Bok, Tomas, Reforming the Polish Economic System., 1991 (Box 1)
  - Boone, Torrence, The Impact of Risk Aversion on the Distributional Patterns of Blacks in the Labor Market., 1991 (Box 1)
  - Cha, Joseph, Below-Cost-Timber-Sales: Economic and Environmental Consequences., 1991 (Box 1)
  - Chang, David, A comparison of Optimal and Heuristic Search Strategies., 1991 (Box 1)
  - Diffendal, Ed, Conclusion and Implications of the Random Walk Hypothesis for the Casual Investor., 1991 (Box 1)
  - Dirks, David, The Future of Fiscal Sovereignty in the European Monetary Union Lessons Learned from the United States., 1991 (Box 1)
  - Feldman, Andrew, Environmental Degredation and High Fertility in sub-Saharan Africa., 1991 (Box 1)
  - Fisher, Mark, The Passing of the Lords of the Lakes and Forests: An Institutional Analysis of the Competition and Collusion in the Canadian Fur Trade, 1800-1825., 1991 (Box 1)
  - Goldin, Jay R., Harnessing the Hong Kong Economy: The Monetary and Exchange Regime Challenges., 1991 (Box 2)
  - Henisz, Witold J., Olympic Myth and Olympic Reality., 1991 (Box 2)
  - Hsaio, Monica, Institutional Investors' Role in Corporate governance: A Survey of th Trends of Institutional Share-Ownership of Large US Corporations., 1991 (Box 2)
  - Kafka, Steven J., Balance or Bias?: The Use of Economic Analysis as a Political Tol in Environmental Policymaking., 1991 (Box 2)
  - Lam, Tuam, The Economics of Cooperatives., 1991 (Box 2)
  - Lee, YongJae, The Industrial Development of South Korea., 1991 (Box 2)
  - Lipschultz, Marc, A Comprehensive Real Estate Pricing Model., 1991 (Box 2)
  - Maggioncaldo, Jeff, Locational Value of Commercial Real Estate in the Twin Cities., 1991 (Box 2)
  - Malueg, Debbie, The Economy of Major League Baseball., 1991 (Box 2)
  - Morgan, Sussana M., The Determinants of Direct Foreign Investment in Finance: An Empirical Study of US Bank Expansion in Developing Countries and the Impact of Host Country Regulations., 1991 (Box 2)
  - Noor, Waseem, Investigating the Social and Environmntal Impacts of Development Projects: A Case Study of the Sardar Sarovar Dam Project., 1991 (Box 2)
  - Rabin, Bradford, Examining the Cost Effectiveness of Comprehensive Prenatal Care for the Poor., 1991 (Box 3)
  - Rosen, Rick, Understanding the Development of the Bahamas: A Structuralist Approach., 1991 (Box 3)
  - Rossol, Joshua, Human Sponges: Labor Subcontracting in the United STates Nuclear Power Industry., 1991 (Box 3)
  - Shirley, Chad, The Allocation of Airside and Terminal Capacity at Bay Area Airports., 1991 (Box 3)
  - Tan, Kokhuan, Links Between National Stock Markets., 1991 (Box 3)
  - Watts, C. Christopher, Setting Priorities for Health Care Provision to the Poor: Theory and Application to Medical Reform in Oregon., 1991 (Box 3)
- Theses, Accession ARCH-1992-099
  - Arney, Richard B., Parallel Developments in the History of Scientific and Economic Thought, Focusing on Rene Descartes, Sir Isaac Newton, Adam Smith, and David Ricardo., April 1992 (Box 1)
  - Barsa, Michael Roland, Transportation and the Environment in the European Community., March 1992 (Box 1)
  - Christofferson, Scott, Efficiency Consequences of Mergers and Acquisitions in the Post-Deregulation Airline Industry., May 1992 (Box 1)
  - Cohen, Jennifer Gail, Assessing the Causes of US Hospital Closures in the 1990s., Spring 1992 (Box 1)
  - Gay, Claudine, Towards the Small Family Norm. An Easterlin and Crimmins' Interpretation of Fertility Trends in Haiti., May 1992 (Box 1)
  - Grigg, Dana Joelee, Exchange Rate Volatility and Quantitative Trade Restrictions: Implications for the GATT., June 1992 (Box 1)
  - Hoshen, Gur, Household Time Allocation, Education, and Their Effects on Child Achievement., May 1992 (Box 1)
  - Lehavi, Ari, Inflation Gone Rampant: Stabilizing the Israeli Economy, 1960-1991., May 1992 (Box 1)
  - Ng, Anita, Liberalization of China: The Tax Question with Hong Kong., June 1992 (Box 1)
  - Palmer, Jeremy, South Korean Strategic Economic Planning: 1962-1990; A Qualified Miracle., June 1992 (Box 1)
  - Rai, Ashok S., Are Democracies More Successful Than Dictatorships at Reducing Chronic Poverty?., May 1992 (Box 2)
  - Rieder, Alyssa C., Reforming the Federal Deposit Insurance System., May 1992 (Box 2)
  - Tolman, Brett, An Analysis of Physical Deliver on Energy Futures Traded on teh New York Mercantile Exchange., Spring 1992 (Box 2)
  - Tsai, Wilson, Leverage and Investment Opportunities: An Empirical Study of the Free Cash Flow Theory of Capital Structure., Spring 1992 (Box 2)
  - Wong, Andrew Kai-Tek, Real, Monetary, and External Sources of Business Cycles in Hong Kong., May 1992 (Box 2)
- Theses, Accession ARCH-2011-152
  - Dang, Ky, Forecasting the growth of the Internet: a diffusion model approach., 1996 (Box 1)
  - Danilchouk, Victoria I., Technical change and the nature of competition: electronic stock brokerage., 1997 (Box 1)
  - Dave, Rishsi, Patterns of success in the Indian software industry., 1996 (Box 1)
  - Dmitriev, Kirill, Small-scale privatization in Ukraine: theory and practice., 1996 (Box 1)
  - Griffin, Devin, Has Ghana positioned its tourism industry to generate sustainable economic development?., 2002 (Box 1)
  - Hudson, Charles, Brazil in the world economy: a survey of the historical path of development and a discussion of Brazil's prospects under Mercosur., 1998 (Box 1)
  - Leventis, Andrew Vernon, Unemployment insurance recipiency in California: a macro and micro evaluation of the state's recent experience., 1993 (Box 1)
  - Llata, George G., Corporate tax integration: the quest to end the double taxation of capital income., 1997 (Box 1)
  - McNary, Robert, The network penetration effects of telecommunications privatization and competition., undated [2000?] (Box 1)
  - Miller, Conrad, Teacher sorting and own-race teacher effects in elementary school., 2009 (Box 1)
  - Rickertsen, Kathryn Y., Virtually true: children's acquisition of false memories in virtual reality., undated [2008?] (Box 1)
  - Halweil, Brian, Huertos familiares: biointensive farming in Mexico: household food production as a means to improve health, income and the environment., 1997 (Box 1)
  - Baeck, Lawrence Keith Eitan, Cigarette demand and government intervention: an examination of state cigarette demand function response to tax increases., undated [1994?] (Box 2)
  - Bennett, Bob M., The Egyptian 1952 agrarian reform and the Japanese 1946 agrarian reform: a comparative study., 1984 (Box 2)
  - Covaci, Mihail A., Devising an effective package of active labor market policies in a transition economy: an empirical analysis of the determinants of unemployment duration in Romania., 1998 (Box 2)
  - Najda, Charles, Low-cost carriers and low fares: competition and concentration in the U.S. airline industry., 2003 (Box 2)
  - Nardinelli, Kate, Do analyst earnings forecast revisions reflect the information contained in stock prices?., 2002 (Box 2)
  - Poon, Julian Wing-Kai, Allocative efficiency and economic growth: the role of education in the economic development of Singapore., 1996 (Box 2)
  - Shotts, Jeffrey A., A study of price dispersionh in the domestic airline industry., undated [1998] (Box 2)
  - Silverman, Jennifer, Genetic testing for breast and ovarian cancer., 2002 (Box 2)
  - Weller, John B., A study of tourism and its effect on the economy of Ely, Minnesota., 1997 (Box 2)
  - Ng, Betty, The potential effects of Korean reunification on South Korean trade., 1993 (Box 2)
  - Khedekar, Sumit, Pricing sovereign debt as an option: theory and evidence. (Box 2)
  - Yasuda, Ayako, The performance and roles of Japanese development banks., 1993 (Box 3)
  - Tilton, Andrew, From socialism to capitalism: unique characteristics of the Eastern German transition to a market economy., 1993 (Box 3)
  - Wan, Donna, Rural women's employment in China under the reforms., 1993 (Box 3)
  - Skuble, Nadine F., University technology licensing: a case study of Stanford's OTL., 1994 (Box 3)
  - McCarroll, Steven Andrew, Capacity, competition and price determination in residential real estate brokerage., 1993 (Box 3)
  - Jayaratnam, Ashwini, How does the black market exchange premium affect foreign direct investment (FDI)?., 2003 (Box 3)
  - Liu, Ben, Product market monopoly and worker compensation: are labor unions required for monopolies to share rents with workers?., 2001 (Box 3)
  - Vardy, Nicholas A., Hungarian enterprise behaviour, Oskar Lange's model of market socialism and the 'soft' budget constraint., 1987 (Box 3)
  - Ahoobim, Oren, Social Security reform: understanding the risks and tradeoffs., 1998 (Box 3)
  - Jain, Vinita, The influence of socioeconomic status and cultural variables on tumor size at diagnosis of breast cancer patients in India., 2000 (Box 3)
  - Dworniak, Maciej W. T., The performance of initial public offerings in the United States and in Poland., 1998 (Box 3)
  - Cottrill, Lance, The price- and profit-concentration relationships in banking., 1994 (Box 3)
  - Chen, Johnny P., Non-performing loan securitization in the People's Republic of China., 2004 (Box 3)
  - Ye, Lei (Sandy), U.S. trade policy and the Pacific Rim, from Fordney-McCumber to the Trade Expansion Act of 1962: a political-economic analysis., 2007 (Box 3)
  - Silverstein, Dana Lyn, The paradox of cooperation in prisoner's dilemma experiments., 1998 (Box 3)
  - Voicu, Cristian, The dynamics of procurement auctions., 2002 (Box 3)
  - Vernon, Jessica, Quantitative restrictions and quality upgrading: the case of the Multi-Fibre Agreement., 2008 (Box 4)
  - Takapong, Saranwut, The "common lender effect": are banking centers crisis carriers?., 2008 (Box 4)
  - Sheu, Wendy, Driving away inequities: uncovering the distributional effects of a gasoline tax., 2003 (Box 4)
  - Stamatian, Andrei, Determinants of bank interest rate spreads and profitability in Romania, 1991-1999., 2000 (Box 4)
  - Campbell, Stewart A., Price effects surrounding composition changes of the S&P 500: aggregate effects since 1999., 2002 (Box 4)
  - Okafor, Chika, Degrees of separation: an alternate cause of discrimination., 2007 (Box 4)
  - Cho, Ann, An empirical study of the effect of downloads on CD album sales., 2004 (Box 4)
  - Warren, Emily, What does migration mean for children left behind? Educational evidence from Guatemala., 2008 (Box 4)
  - Fielding-Singh, Vikram, Reputation buildgin as counterterrorism: theory and evidence., 2005 (Box 4)
  - Droesch, Audrey, Hollywood north: the impact of costs and demarcation rules on the runaway film industry., 2002 (Box 4)
  - Fisher, Douglas, The effects of reimbursement on treatment decisions and outcomes of heart attack patients., 1998 (Box 4)
  - Bishop, Ellie, Angel investors, risk, and social networks., 2001 (Box 4)
  - Campbell, Michelle, Hong Kong, China, and technological change: an application of the product cycle model., 1996 (Box 4)